A Guide to the Dorothy McCombs Collection, 1970-1989
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Dorothy McCombs Collection, 1970-1989
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1995-006
8.6 cu. ft. 19 boxes
The collection contains personal research notes, subject files, and writings; materials relating to the Virginia Tech University Libraries; course notes; dissertation research; work on textiles and arts & crafts history; genealogy notes; brochures on historic sites around Virginia; and maps collected by Dorothy McCombs. Materials date from about 1970-1989.
McCombs, Dorothy F., 1923-1990
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Dorothy McCombs Collection was donated to Special Collections prior to 1995.
Biographical Note
Dorothy McCombs graduated from VPI in 1976. She went on to work in the libraries as a reference librarian and Appalachian history bibliographer until 1990. Over the course of her career, she researched genealogy, local history/Appalachian history, textiles, and more.
Scope and Content
The collection contains personal research notes, subject files, and writings; materials relating to the Virginia Tech University Libraries; course notes; dissertation research; work on textiles and arts & crafts history; genealogy notes; brochures on historic sites around Virginia; and maps collected by Dorothy McCombs. Materials date from about 1970-1989.
Although materials cover a wide range of topics and regions, particular emphases include research notes on Appalachian textile production, information on historic Blacksburg and Montgomery County, notes on the Preston family and the Smithfield Plantation, and local/regional genealogy. There are also papers relating to McCombs tenure as a reference librarian at Virginia Tech.
McCombs extensively researched textiles, of which she published “National Context and the Local Experience of Domestic Textile Manufacture in Montgomery County, VA 1776-1830.” Several other publications found in this collection include “Local History and Genealogical Research in University Libraries,” and her thesis, “Virginia Cloth, Early Textiles in Virginia: Particularly in the Backcountry between the Blue Ridge and Alleghany Mountains until 1830”. There is also a copy of her unpublished manuscript, "Virginia Cloth: Early Textiles in Montgomery County, 1776-1830” in the collection as well.
Arrangement
The Dorothy McCombs Collection is organized into nine series by material type. Series include: Brochures; Maps; Subject Files; Publications (in two suberies--Publications by McCombs and Publications by Others); Notes; Census Records; Textiles/Arts & Crafts; Library Materials; and Professional and Personal Papers.
Within each series, materials are arranged alphabetically by folder title. Whenever possible, original folder titles, created by McCombs, were retained. Unfoldered materials were described by Special Collections staff.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Preston family, Montgomery County, Va.
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); Smithfield Plantation House (Blacksburg, Va.); University Archives; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Series I: Brochures
  - Charlottesville-- Brochures (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Fredericksburg, Virginia-- Brochures, Slides (Box-folder 5-9)
  - Georgia-- Brochures (Box-folder 5-16)
  - Kentucky-- Brochures (Box-folder 6-19)
  - Lexington, Virginia-- Brochures (Box-folder 6-22)
  - North Carolina-- Brochures (Box-folder 12-3)
  - Pennsylvania-- Brochures (Box-folder 12-12)
  - Richmond, Virginia Brochures (Box-folder 14-4)
  - Roanoke, Roanoke Valley Brochures (Box-folder 14-5)
  - Smithfield-- Brochures (Box-folder 14-11)
  - Tennessee-- Brochures (Box-folder 15-10)
  - Virginia-- Brochures (Box-folder 17-3)
  - Washington County, Virginia-- Abington Brochures (Box-folder 17-12)
  - West Virginia-- Brochures (Box-folder 18-3)
- Series II: Maps
  - Blacksburg-- Maps (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Maps (Box-folder 8-6)
  - Maps--Travel (Box-folder 8-7)
- Series III: Subject Files
  - Ads (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Aldridge-- IRA, c. 1805-1867 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Alexandria-- Pamphlets and Fliers (Box-folder 1-5)
  - American Association for State and Local History (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Appalachia-- Clippings and Articles (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Appalachian Studies (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Appalachian-- Studies Conference, 1988 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Appalink-- Newsletter, 1988 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Appalachian-- Solitude, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Appraisals by Appointed Neighbors-- Inventories of Sales, 1808 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - APVA, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - APVA, 1967-1989 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - APVA-- Montgomery County, c 1980-1981 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Asche-- Volunteerism, 1987 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Association for the Bibliography of History (1/2), 1990 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Association for the Bibliography of History (2/2), 1983-1986 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Black Family and VPI notes (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Blacksburg (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Blacksburg, Virginia-- Articles (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Blacksburg-- Calendars with Pictures and Prints of Blacksburg and Montgomery Country, 1980, 1986 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Blacksburg-- Churches, Religion (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Blacksburg-- Clippings (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Blacksburg-- History (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Blacksburg, Virginia-- Information (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Blacksburg-- Landscapes (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Blacksburg-- Pictures (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Blacksburg-- Regional Art Association (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Blacksburg-- Residents, 1940 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Blacksburg, Virginia (Box-folder 3-2)
  - Blacks of Blacksburg (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Bowden, Mitchell 9-1-703 PO Box 1904 Roanoke Valley Historical Society Center in the Square, Roanoke VA 24008, 1988 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Breckinridge, Lucy-- Journal of a VA Girl, 1862-1864 (Box-folder 3-5)
  - Bronson J+R-- The Domestic Manufacturer's Assistant, 1949 (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Christiansburg, Virginia, 1988 (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Colonial Virginia/Appalachia-- Manufacturing and History (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Conference on the Appalachian Frontier, May 1985 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Committees-- Legislative, 1987 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - Committees Landmark, 1987 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - Craft Schools, Folk Schools (Box-folder 4-4)
  - Crossnore School, c. 1976 (Box-folder 4-5)
  - Delaware Woolen Industry (Box-folder 4-6)
  - Delta Kappa Gamma, 1988 (Box-folder 4-7)
  - Distinguished Virginia Women by Gertrude Blair (Box-folder 4-8)
  - Draper's Meadows, Virginia (Box-folder 4-9)
  - Eastman (Box-folder 4-11)
  - Eaton, Allen-- Mountain Handicrafts, 1930 (Box-folder 4-12)
  - Ferrum College-- Blue Ridge Institute (Box-folder 5-3)
  - Fireside Industries (Box-folder 5-4)
  - Fitness Connection (Box-folder 5-5)
  - Flax (Box-folder 5-6)
  - Folk Songs (Box-folder 5-7)
  - Folk Tales/Oral History (Box-folder 5-8)
  - From Assoc. to Rev. (Box-folder 5-10)
  - From Patrick County Project Blue Ridge Mission School (Box-folder 5-11)
  - Gandhi, 1975 (Box-folder 5-12)
  - Gazeteers of Virginia Including Giles and Montgomery (Box-folder 5-13)
  - Genealogy (Box-folder 5-14)
  - Genealogy-- Orientation (Box-folder 5-15)
  - Germanicus A. Kent (Box-folder 5-17)
  - Giles County (Box-folder 5-18)
  - Giles County (Box-folder 5-19)
  - Giles County-- Historical Society (Box-folder 5-20)
  - Greenfield (Box-folder 6-1)
  - Historic Blacksburg-- Assorted Copied Pictures (Box-folder 6-3)
  - Historic Preservation (Box-folder 6-4)
  - History-- Appalachian (Box-folder 6-5)
  - History-- Bibliography/Library (Box-folder 6-6)
  - History-- Houses (Box-folder 6-7)
  - History-- Preston (Box-folder 6-8)
  - History-- Social (Box-folder 6-9)
  - Home Life in Colonial Days-- Alice Morse Earle, 1931 (Box-folder 6-10)
  - Home Manufactures (Box-folder 6-11)
  - Illustrations (Box-folder 6-12)
  - "In Old Blacksburg" by Dr. (W.B.) Conway, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 6-13)
  - James Miller Oral History (Box-folder 6-16)
  - Keep (Box-folder 6-17)
  - Kegley-- Family Institute, June 1988 (Box-folder 6-18)
  - Landis Valley Farm Museum, Pennsylvania (Box-folder 6-20)
  - Lewis, Mrs. Letita Preston (Floyd) Letters and St. John's Catholic Chapel (Box-folder 6-21)
  - LFA--Visiting Scholar, 1981 (Box-folder 6-23)
  - Local History (Box-folder 8-1)
  - Local History and Genealogy (Box-folder 8-2)
  - Lynchburg (Box-folder 8-3)
  - Mabry Mill, Floyd County (Box-folder 8-4)
  - MacMillan (Box-folder 8-5)
  - Mary Draper Ingles (Box-folder 8-8)
  - Miller, Lewis (Box-folder 10-10)
  - Mills-- Fueling (Box-folder 10-11)
  - Minutes (Box-folder 10-12)
  - Montgomery County (Box-folder 10-13)
  - Montgomery County (Box-folder 10-14)
  - Montgomery County-- Articles (Box-folder 11-1)
  - Montgomery County-- Clippings (Box-folder 11-2)
  - Montgomery County-- Historical Inventory (Box-folder 11-3)
  - Montgomery County-- History of (Box-folder 11-4)
  - Montgomery County-- Information 1879, 1876, 1890 (Box-folder 11-5)
  - Montgomery County-- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 11-6)
  - Montgomery County-- 120th Anniversary Clippings from News Messenger (Box-folder 11-7)
  - Morgan, Clarita (Box-folder 11-8)
  - Mountain Lake (Box-folder 11-9)
  - Museum of the American Frontier (Box-folder 11-10)
  - Museum of American Frontier Culture (Box-folder 11-11)
  - National Archives (Box-folder 11-12)
  - Newbern, Virginia (Box-folder 11-13)
  - New River Historical Society (Box-folder 11-14)
  - New River and New River Valley (Box-folder 11-15)
  - New River Valley Preservation League Documents (Box-folder 11-16)
  - New River Valley Preservation League Newsletter (Box-folder 11-17)
  - New River Valley Preservation League Stationary (Box-folder 11-18)
  - New River Valley Preservation League (Box-folder 11-19)
  - New River Valley Travel (Box-folder 12-1)
  - NRHS (Box-folder 12-4)
  - NRVPL (Box-folder 12-5)
  - Outline Manufacturing Research-- Colonial (Box-folder 12-6)
  - Patrick County (Box-folder 12-7)
  - Patrick County Project (Box-folder 12-8)
  - Patrick County Project-- Oral History Collection (Box-folder 12-9)
  - Patrick Henry (Box-folder 12-10)
  - Pictures (Box-folder 12-13)
  - Preservation Alliance of Virginia, September/December 1987 (Box-folder 12-14)
  - Preservation-- Other, October 1988 (Box-folder 12-15)
  - Prestons-- Articles and Biographies (Box-folder 12-16)
  - Prestons-- Clippings (Box-folder 13-1)
  - Prestons-- Family Cemetery (Box-folder 13-2)
  - Prestons-- Family Papers (Box-folder 13-3)
  - Prestons-- Guide to Preservation of Virginia Antiquities (Box-folder 13-4)
  - Prestons-- Information from Bolar News Service (Box-folder 13-5)
  - Prestons-- Inventories and Wills (Box-folder 13-6)
  - Prestons-- Letters, c 1843 (Box-folder 13-7)
  - Prestons-- Papers and Copies of Letters, 1783-1843 (Box-folder 13-8)
  - Pulaski County, c 1988 (Box-folder 13-9)
  - Pulaski County (Box-folder 13-10)
  - Radford, 1976-1985 (Box-folder 14-2)
  - Reynolds Homestead-- Mary, Dave Britt 8-703-694-7181 Box 21 Critz, VA 24082 (Box-folder 14-3)
  - Roanoke Valley Historical Society, c 1989 (Box-folder 14-6)
  - Shawsville, Virginia, c 1988 (Box-folder 14-8)
  - Significance of Ingles Ferry and History of Ingles Ferry by Francis Burke Fitzpatrick, 1936-1985 (Box-folder 14-9)
  - Smithfield-- Articles (Box-folder 14-10)
  - Smithfield-- Clippings and Events, 1979-1986 (Box-folder 14-12)
  - Smithfield-- Clippings on History, Restoration, Dedication (Box-folder 14-13)
  - Smithfield-- Docents (Box-folder 14-14)
  - Smithfield-- Events, Announcements, and Invitations, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 14-15)
  - Smithfield-- Garden Week Tours (Box-folder 15-1)
  - Smithfield-- Pictures (Box-folder 15-2)
  - Smithfield-- Tour Plans and Docents, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 15-4)
  - Southland Travel Service Letter from Allen Montgomery, c 1987 (Box-folder 15-5)
  - Southwest Virginia (Box-folder 15-6)
  - Springs in Montgomery County (Box-folder 15-7)
  - Statistics (Box-folder 15-8)
  - Today (Box-folder 16-12)
  - USS Potomac-- Specifications for Materials Correspondence, c 1940 (Box-folder 16-13)
  - Virginia Landmarks (Box-folder 16-14)
  - Virginia Landmarks Community (also see "Houses") (Box-folder 16-15)
  - Virginia Womens Cultural History Project (Box-folder 16-16)
  - Valentine Museum, c 1974 (Box-folder 16-17)
  - Vernacular Architecture, 1933-1985 (Box-folder 16-18)
  - Virginia Tech-- Clippings (Box-folder 17-4)
  - Virginia Tech Campus Guides (Box-folder 17-8)
  - Virginia to 1830 (Box-folder 17-9)
  - Washington County, c 1974 (Box-folder 17-11)
  - Williams, Brenda and Johnston, Jane,c 1987 (Box-folder 18-4)
  - Word Perfect (Box-folder 18-6)
  - Wythe County, 1984 (Box-folder 18-7)
- Series IV: Publications
  - Subseries I: Publications by McCombs
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Publication: Local History and Genealogical Research in University Libraries, 1988 (Box-folder 10-2)
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Publication: National Context and the Local Experience of Domestic Textile Manufacture in Montgomery County, VA 1776-1830 (Box-folder 10-3)
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Thesis 1/5 (Box-folder 10-5)
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Thesis 2/5 (Box-folder 10-6)
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Thesis 3/5 (Box-folder 10-7)
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Thesis 4/5 (Box-folder 10-8)
    - McCombs, Dorothy-- Thesis 5/5 (Box-folder 10-9)
    - Thesis Charts (Box-folder 16-10)
  - Subseries II: Other Publications
    - Activity Report--McCombs, 1977-1987 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - The Mountain Laurel (Box-folder 16-8)
    - To Carolyn (Box-folder 16-11)
    - Virginia Tech-- SPECTRUM, 1982-1989 (Box-folder 17-6)
    - Virginia Tech-- TECH GRAM, May 1976 (Box-folder 17-7)
- Series V: Notes
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Note cards (Box-folder 8-11)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Notes (Box-folder 8-12)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Notes (Box-folder 8-13)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Notes (Box-folder 9-1)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Notes (Box-folder 9-2)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Notes (Box-folder 9-3)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Notes on Genealogy (Box-folder 9-4)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Research Notes (Box-folder 10-4)
  - Shackelford's Notes (Box-folder 14-7)
- Series VI: Census Records
  - Census (1790)-- Hamilton Report on Manufactures (Box-folder 3-7)
  - Census (1810) (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Census (1820) (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Census (1820)-- Manufacturing Report (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Census (1840) (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Montgomery County-- 1850 Census (Box-folder 10-15)
- Series VII: Textiles/Arts & Crafts
  - Appalachian-- Arts and Crafts, 1972-1988 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Africa- Textiles (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Arts and Crafts-- Government, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - Arts and Crafts-- Movement (Box-folder 1-18)
  - Cotton (Box-folder 4-3)
  - Dyeing, c. 1981 (Box-folder 4-10)
  - Ellis, Asa-- The Country Dyer's Assistant, 1749 (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Fabrics- Reproductions, 1980 (Box-folder 5-1)
  - Hemp (Box-folder 6-2)
  - Irish Spinning, Dyeing, Weaving, 1978 (Box-folder 6-14)
  - Jacquard, 1976 (Box-folder 6-15)
  - Linen (Box-folder 7-24)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Personal Interior Decorating (Samples in separate box) (Box-folder 9-5)
  - North Carolina-- Arts and Crafts (Box-folder 12-2)
  - Patterns for Woven Goods (Box-folder 12-11)
  - Quilts, 1974 (Box-folder 14-1)
  - Samples of "McCombs Interior Decorating" in Box 9 Folder 5 (Box 19)
  - Smithfield-- Textiles (Box-folder 15-3)
  - Tennessee- Crafts (Box-folder 15-11)
  - Textiles (Box-folder 15-12)
  - Textiles-- Dyeing (Box-folder 15-13)
  - Textiles-- England and Scotland (Box-folder 16-1)
  - Textiles-- Illustrations (Box-folder 16-2)
  - Textiles-- Manufacturing Appendix/Acknowledgements (Box-folder 16-3)
  - Textiles-- Manufacturing Listings 1770-1830, primarily 1810, 1770-1830 (Box-folder 16-4)
  - Textiles-- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 16-5)
  - Textiles-- Spinning (Box-folder 16-6)
  - Textiles-- Spinning, Dyeing, Weaving, c 1974 (Box-folder 16-7)
  - The Virginia Mountain Crafts Guild, c 1983 (Box-folder 16-9)
  - Virginia Textile history, Chapters I-VI with Bibliographies (Box-folder 17-1)
  - Virginia-- Arts and Crafts Councils (Box-folder 17-2)
  - Virginia-- Silk (Box-folder 17-5)
  - Weaving, 1819-1989 (Box-folder 18-1)
  - West Virginia-- Arts and Crafts (Box-folder 18-2)
  - Wool, c 1947 (Box-folder 18-5)
  - Textile Samples (Box 19)
- Series VIII: Library Materials
  - Library-- African American History (Box-folder 7-1)
  - Library-- American History, Basic List (Box-folder 7-2)
  - Library-- Appalachian (Box-folder 7-3)
  - Library-- Archival Materials Access to ... (Box-folder 7-4)
  - Library-- Bibliographies Instruction, History (Box-folder 7-5)
  - Library-- British (Box-folder 7-6)
  - Library-- Census (Box-folder 7-7)
  - Library-- Civil War (Box-folder 7-8)
  - Library-- Compiled Service Records (Box-folder 7-9)
  - Library-- Education (Box-folder 7-10)
  - Library-- Government Documents/Historical Research (Box-folder 7-11)
  - Library-- Historical Research (Box-folder 7-12)
  - Library-- Law (Box-folder 7-13)
  - Library-- Library Orientation (Box-folder 7-14)
  - Library-- Montgomery County (Box-folder 7-15)
  - Library-- New River (Box-folder 7-16)
  - Library-- Periodical List (Box-folder 7-17)
  - Library-- SW Virginia (Box-folder 7-18)
  - Library-- Technology (Box-folder 7-19)
  - Library-- The Appalachian Collection (Box-folder 7-20)
  - Library-- United States Constitution (Box-folder 7-21)
  - Library-- Virginia (Box-folder 7-22)
  - Library-- Womens Studies (Box-folder 7-23)
- Series IX: Professional and Personal Papers
  - EDAE/FST 4980 Notes 1/3, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - EDAE/FST 4980 Notes 2/3, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 4-14)
  - EDAE/FST 4980 Notes 3/3, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Faculty Womens Club, 1988 (Box-folder 5-2)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Articles (Box-folder 8-9)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Dissertation Paperwork and Letters (Box-folder 8-10)
  - McCombs, Dorothy-- Personal Photographs and Letters (Box-folder 10-1)
  - Telephone Numbers and Names (Box-folder 15-9)
  - Vitae/Memorandum of McCombs, c 1989 (Box-folder 17-10)